A Guide to the Theodore Dreiser Collection, 1921-1922
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Theodore Dreiser Collection, 1921-1922
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
6220-f
This collection consists of 16 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was deposited in the library in 1981.
Contents List
- Letters
  - R. L. Simon, New York, to W. W. Lange, Milwaukee, Wisconsin 1921 Nov 7, TLS, 1 p.
    States that he has no criticisms of Theodore Dreiser's work; suggests he asks editor of New York Evening Post for bibliography; writes that Boni Liveright regards Dreiser as a great American realist and is proud to be his publisher; mentions public opinion, sales, and royalties.
  - [W. W. Lange], Milwaukee, to Atlantic Monthly, New York 1921 Nov 28, TL, 1 p. Carbon.
    Asks if they have any published or written criticism on Theodore Dreiser, particularly on Sister Carrie, Jennie Gerhardt, or The Financier; asks for opinions of Dreiser; praises Dreiser's work.
  - [W. W. Lange], Milwaukee, to Literary Digest, New York 1921 Nov 28, TL, 1 p. Carbon.
    Same as previous item.
  - Henry S. Canby to W. W. Lange, Milwaukee 1921 Nov 30, TLS, 1 p.
    Writes that he reviewed Theodore Dreiser's books when they appeared; respects Dreiser's work, but believes it is more substance than form.
  - H. W. Ralston, New York, to W. W. Lange, Milwaukee 1921 Dec 2, TLS, 1 p.
    Discusses collection written material on Theodore Dreiser; mentions hiring Dreiser as associate editor of Smith's Magazine; knows Dreiser intimately; regrets they cannot do greater justice to Dreiser and his work.
  - Editor, Atlantic Monthly, Boston, to W. W. Lange, Milwaukee 1921 Dec 3, TLS, 1 p.
    Discusses varied opinions of Theodore Dreiser's work and publishing difficulty with Sister Carrie.
  - C. H. Holmes, Butterick Pat. Co., New York, to W. W. Lange, Milwaukee 1921 Dec 5, TLS, 1 p.
    Writes that he does not recall any criticisms of Dreiser's work that would interest him; suggests he get index to periodical literature in library where he can find references to Dreiser and his work.
  - Alexander Harvey, New York, to W. W. Lange, Milwaukee 1921 Dec 5, TLS, 1 p.
    Includes TL carbon, 1921 Nov 28, W. W. Lange to Current Opinion; calls Theodore Dreiser a writer of power and Sister Carrie a work of genius; believes Jennie Gerhardt reveals mastery of narrative and insight into human character; compliments The Financier; suggests her write Dreiser directly for clippings.
  - William Lengel, New York, to W. W. Lange, Milwaukee 1921 Dec 6, TLS, 1 p.
    Includes TL carbon, 1921 Nov 28, W. W. Lange to Hearst's Publishing Co.; believes that Theodore Dreiser comes near to being America's greatest novelist of the time; suggests Boni & Liveright or H. L. Mencken could help in search.
  - [W. W. Lange] to The Fortnightly Review1921 Dec 12, TL. Carbon.
    Copy of letter to Atlantic Monthly.
  - Grant Richards, London, to W. W. Lange, Milwaukee 1921 Dec 25, TLS, 1 p. W/env.
    Explains that he has written letters praising Dreiser, but not for publication, excepting a quotation of him on jacket of Sister Carrie; writes that he cannot say where Dreiser's work is praised in England; argues he is one of the leading men of letters in the United States; suggests Frank Harris could tell where he wrote regarding Dreiser's work.
  - W. L. Courtney, London, to W. W. Lange, Milwaukee 1921 Dec 29, TLS, 1 p. W/env.
    Writes that no article by Dreiser was published in Fortnightly Review; holds a very high opinion of his work; suggests he write to Arnold Bennett, Edmund Goose, and Hugh Walpole.
  - W. George, New York, to W. W. Lange, New York 1922 Jan 14, ALS, 2 p. W/env.
    Thinks of Dreiser as important, though he has never written of him; knows The Financier and The Genius best; believes Dreiser has captured flavor of American life, but is hampered by incoherence of form, crude ideas, and vulgar outlook; believes American literature to be more vital than that of England or France.
  - S. W. Linn, Chicago, to W. W. w/envLange, MIlwaukee 1922 Apr 3, ALS, 2 p.
    Writes that Sister Carrie is often called the most effective novel written by a Chicago author; compliments Jennie Gerhardt, and The Financier; thinks much less of The Titan and The Genius; thinks Theodore Dreiser's purpose is to present life as he sees it; comments on Dreiser's style, morality, and literary rank.
  - John Farrar, Geo. Doran Co., New York, to W. W. Lange, Milwaukee 1924 Jan 23, TLS, 1 p.
    Writes that Spotlight has not yet analyzed Theodore Dreiser; refers him to article by Edward J. Smith, March 1921; compliments Dreiser's technique.
- "Professor [James Weber] Linn analyzes American fiction," 1922 Mar, Clipping, 1 p.
  Speech at College Club meeting; believes Sister Carrie to be a good book and The Titan to be a bad one; believes bad fiction is a menace to national taste.